<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html>
  <head>
    <title>Steps to block spam with Pyzor</title>
  </head>

  <body>
    <h1>Steps to block spam with Pyzor</h1>

    <h2>Introduction</h2>
    
    <p>
      This document describes general overall steps you should
      take to use Pyzor effectively.
    </p>
    
    <h2>Steps</h2>
    <ol>
      <li><h3>Blacklist</h3>
    <p>
      The first step you should take on your incoming mail is to
      process it with a blacklist.  A <dfn>blacklist</dfn> blocks all mail
      that can be <em>definitively</em> and <em>deterministically</em>
      marked as spam.  A common technique is to keep a list of commercial
      spammers and block them at this step.  For example,
      you may want to block all mail coming from mediatrec.com, since
      they are spammers; they would then be blacklisted.
    </p>
  </li>
    
    <li><h3>Whitelist</h3>
    <p>
      The second step you should take on your incoming mail is to
      process it with a whitelist.  A <dfn>whitelist</dfn> allows
      in all mail that can be <em>definitively</em>
      and <em>deterministically</em> marked as coming from a
      &quot;good source&quot;.  This includes mailing coming
      from personal people you know and mailing lists.
    </p>
  </li>
    
    <li>
      <h3>Content-based solutions</h3>
    <p>
      Content-based solutions look at the body of an email, and
      use methods that are <em>not definitive</em>
      and <em>heuristics-based</em> to mark things as spam.
    </p>
    <p>
      It is <em>vital</em> that you use content-based
      solutions  <strong>after whitelisting</strong>,
      since they can mark 'good' mail as spam.  Any system
      which uses heuristics or non-definitive methods should
      always uses these methods as a <em>fallback</em>
      from the more assured <a href="#blacklist">blacklist</a>
      and <a href="#whitelist">whitelist</a>.  <strong>To use these
	systems with missing, incomplete, or incorrect whitelists is
	to show haphazard care for marking 'good' mail as spam.
      </strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      Examples of content-based solutions are:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
	<strong><a href="http://pyzor.sourceforge.net/">Pyzor</a></strong>,
	which calculates digests of parts of mail, and matches it with
	what other people have gotten.
      </li>
      <li>
	<a href="http://spamassassin.taint.org/">SpamAssassin</a>,
	which uses heuristics such as looking for many caps along
	with a <a href="http://spamassassin.taint.org/tests.html">scoring
	  method</a> to mark things as spam.  Note that products
	such as SpamAssassin often use products such as Pyzor
	as part of their tests.
      </li>
    </ul>
    
    </li>
    
  </ol>
    
  </body>
</html>
